My story actually began when I was four years old
بدأت قصتي حقيقة .. عندما كنت في الرابعة من عمري
and my family moved to a new neighborhood
عندما انتقلت مع عائلتي الى حي جديد
in our hometown of Savannah, Georgia.
في مدينتي .. سافانها في جورجيا
And this was the 1960s
وكان ذلك في ال1960
when actually all the streets in this neighborhood
عندما كانت كل الشوارع حينها
were named after Confederate war generals.
مسماة تبعاً لجنرالات الحرب حينها
We lived on Robert E. Lee Boulevard.
كنا نعيش في روبرت لي بلدف
And when I was five,
وعندما كنت في الخامسة عمري
my parents gave me an orange Schwinn Sting-Ray bicycle.
اشترى لي والدي دراجة هوائية برتقالية اللون
It had a swooping banana seat and those ape hanger handlebars
كانت تملك مقعد متحرك اصفر اللون .. و مسكات يد بنية اللون وبفراء يشبه فراء القردة
that made the rider look like an orangutan.
كنت أبدو عليها مثل انسان غابة
That's why they were called ape hangers.
وتدعى تلك المسكات مسكات القرد
They were actually modeled on hotrod motorcycles of the 1960s,
لقد صممت حينها تلك الدراجة تبعاً للدراجة النارية "هوت رود" التي اشتهرت عام 1960
which I'm sure my mom didn't know.
والتي لم تكن تعلم عنها والدتي
And one day I was exploring this cul-de-sac
وذات يوم كنت استكشف الناحية
hidden away a few streets away.
واحاول تجاوز بعض الطرق العامة
And I came back,
ورأيت طريقاً جميلاً
and I wanted to turn around and get back to that street more quickly,
فحاولت ان ألتف واعود إليه بسرعة
so I decided to turn around in this big street
وذلك أثناء تواجدي في ..
that intersected our neighborhood,
التقاطع الموجود في ناحيتنا
and wham! I was hit by a passing sedan.
و فجأة .. اصبت بسيارة عابرة
My mangled body flew in one direction,
فطار جسمي في ناحية
my mangled bike flew in the other.
ودراجتي في ناحية اخرى
And I lay on the pavement stretching over that yellow line,
وم ثم وقعت على الخط الاصفر المرسوم على الاسفلت .. واصبت بجراح
and one of my neighbors came running over.
ورآني احد الجيران .. فهرول نحوي
"Andy, Andy, how are you doing?" she said, using the name of my older brother.
" أندي .. أندي .. هل انت بخير .؟ " لقد استخدم اسم أخي الكبير
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
"I'm Bruce," I said, and promptly passed out.
" انا بروس " هكذا قلت .. قبل أن يغمى علي
I broke my left femur that day --
لقد كسرت عظم فخذي حينها
it's the largest bone in your body --
انها العظمة الاكبر في الجسم
and spent the next two months in a body cast
وقضيت شهرين مجبساً بالجبس
that went from my chin to the tip of my toe
من ذقني .. وحتى اخمص قدمي
to my right knee,
مروراً بركبتي
and a steel bar went from my right knee
كما ان قضيباً معدنياً زرع من ركبتي اليمنى
to my left ankle.
حتى كاحلي الايسر
And for the next 38 years,
ومنذ 38 عام ..
that accident was the only medically interesting thing
هذا الحادث كان التجربة الطبية الحقيقية
that ever happened to me.
التي مررت بها
In fact, I made a living by walking.
في الحقيقة .. انا اعيش عن طريق المشي
I traveled around the world, entered different cultures,
انا اسافر حول العالم .. واتعرف على ثقافات مختلفة
wrote a series of books about my travels,
واكتب قصص عن سفرياتي
including "Walking the Bible."
منها " السير على خطى الانجيل "
I hosted a television show by that name
وقدمت برنامجاً عنوانه نفس الكتاب
on PBS.
على قناة " بي بي اس "
I was, for all the world, the "walking guy."
وكنت بالنسبة للعالم .. الرجل الذي يمشي
Until, in May 2008,
حتى شهر مايو 2008
a routine visit to my doctor
و من ثم وبسبب زيارة روتينية الى طبيبي
and a routine blood test
وبعد عمل فحص دم ورتيني
produced evidence in the form of an alkaline phosphatase number
اظهر رقم قلويات الفوسفاتيز
that something might be wrong with my bones.
ان هناك مشكلة ما تطرأ في عظامي
And my doctor, on a whim, sent me to get a full-body bone scan,
وقال طبيبي انه يجب ان اخضع لفحص عظام شامل
which showed that there was some growth in my left leg.
اظهر ان هناك نمو جسم غريب في رجلي اليسرى
That sent me to an X-ray, then to an MRI.
ومن ثم تم ارسالي الى تصوير اشعة اكس .. ومن ثم الى الرنين المغناطيسي
And one afternoon, I got a call from my doctor.
وفي احد الايام .. جائني اتصال من طبيبي
"The tumor in your leg
يخبرني ان الورم الذي في قدمي
is not consistent with a benign tumor."
تجاوز كونه ورماً
I stopped walking,
ان هذا قد يحد من قدرتي على السير لاحقاً
and it took my mind a second to convert that double negative
وقد تطلب ثواني الامر لكي اكتشف ان الامر
into a much more horrifying negative.
مريعٌ جداً
I have cancer.
فانا مصاب بالسرطان
And to think that the tumor was in the same bone,
والاكثر جللاً .. ان السرطان في نفس العظمة
in the same place in my body
في نفس المكان
as the accident 38 years earlier --
الذي تعرضت فيه لحادثة فيه منذ 38 عام
it seemed like too much of a coincidence.
ان الامر من المحال ان يكون مصادفة
So that afternoon, I went back to my house,
وذلك المساء .. عدت الى منزلي
and my three year-old identical twin daughters, Eden and Tybee Feiler,
وكان هناك إبنتي التوأم ذوات الثلاث اعوام . إيدين و تيبي فيلير
came running to meet me.
وقد جريا نحوي
They'd just turned three,
وقد رأيتهما 3 اشخاص
and they were into all things pink and purple.
وكان كل شيء يشع باللون الزهري والبنفسجي
In fact, we called them Pinkalicious and Purplicious --
في الحقيقة نحن ندعوهما اللذيذة الزهرية .. واللذيذة البنفسجية
although I must say, our favorite nickname
على الرغم من ان لقبهما المفضلين
occurred on their birthday, April 15th.
لُقبا به في 15 من ابريل
When they were born at 6:14 and 6:46
حيث انهما ولدا في 6:14 .. و 6:46
on April 15, 2005,
في 15 من ابريل
our otherwise grim, humorless doctor looked at his watch,
فقال الطبيب الذي كان يفتقر الى روح الدعابة حينها بعد ان نظر الى ساعته
and was like, "Hmm, April 15th -- tax day.
مممم .. انه 15 من ابريل .. يوم الضرائب
Early filer and late filer."
لنسميهما " فيلر المبكرة " .. " فيلر المتأخرة " تستحق الضرائب بعد 6:30 ص
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
The next day I came to see him. I was like, "Doctor, that was a really good joke."
في اليوم التالي قدمت اليه واخبرته .. دكتور لقد كانت نكتة جميلة حينها
And he was like, "You're the writer, kid."
فقال لي .. يا صديقي .. انت الكاتب ولست انا ...
Anyway -- so they had just turned three,
حسنا .. لنعد الى القصة .. لقد كانوا قد بلغوا الثالثة للتو
and they came and they were doing this dance they had just made up
و جروا نحوي وكانوا يؤدون رقصة كانوا للتو قد اخترعوها
where they were twirling faster and faster until they tumbled to the ground,
وكانوا يدورون بشدة ويقفزون حتى سقطوا على الارض من الاعياء
laughing with all the glee in the world.
وهم يضحكون بشدة و يملؤون المكان فرحاً
I crumbled.
هنا انهرت انا تماما
I kept imagining all the walks I might not take with them,
كنت اتخيل في عقلي .. كل تلك الرحلات التي لن استطيع الذهاب معهم بها
the art projects I might not mess up,
والانشطة الفنية التي لن استطيع الحضور لها
the boyfriends I might not scowl at,
والاصدقاء الذين لن استطيع التهجم عليهم
the aisles I might not walk down.
ومشية ليلة العرس التي لن استطيع السير بها
Would they wonder who I was, I thought.
هل سوف يتذكرونني .. كنت هكذا افكر
Would they yearn for my approval,
هل سوف يطلبون موافقتي
my love, my voice?
مباركتي .. حبي .. صوتي
A few days later, I woke with an idea
وبعد عدة ايام خطرت على بالي فكرة
of how I might give them that voice.
كيف يمكنني ان اوصل لهم صوتي
I would reach out to six men
قلت .. لا بد ان اتواصل مع 6 رجال
from all parts of my life
من محيطي .. جزء من حياتي
and ask them to be present
واخبرهم ان يوصلوا رسائلي
in the passages of my daughters' lives.
الى بناتي .. اثناء حياتهم
"I believe my girls will have plenty of opportunities in their lives,"
" اعتقد ان بناتي سوف تتاح لهن الكثير من الفرص في هذه الحياة "
I wrote these men.
هكذا كتبت لهم ..
"They'll have loving families and welcoming homes,
" سوف يملكون عائلات محبة .. وبيوت دافئة "
but they may not have me.
ربما لن اكون موجودا معهم
They may not have their dad.
وربما والدهم سيكون حينها قد رحل
Will you help be their dad?"
هل تساعدوني .. لكي تعوضوا هذا النقص
And I said to myself
وقلت لنفسي
I would call this group of men "the Council of Dads."
سوف اقوم باطلاق لقب " مجلس الآباء " على هذه المجموعة
Now as soon as I had this idea,
وما ان خطرت على بالي هذه الفكرة
I decided I wouldn't tell my wife. Okay.
حتى قررت ان اخبر زوجتي .. حناً
She's a very upbeat,
لقد كانت إمرأة رائعة مبتهجة
naturally excited person.
انها متحمسة بالفطرة
There's this idea in this culture -- I don't have to tell you --
وهناك فكرة في مجتمعنا تقول .. اعتقد انكم تعرفونها
that you sort of "happy" your way through a problem.
انه يمكن بالايجابية ايجاد الحلول لكل المشاكل
We should focus on the positive.
فنحن على الدوام يجب ان نركز على الايجابية
My wife, as I said, she grew up outside of Boston.
لقد تربينا انا وزوجتي خارج بوسطن
She's got a big smile. She's got a big personality.
هي تملك ابتسامة كبيرة .. وشخصية رائعة
She's got big hair --
وشعرٌ كثيفٌ ايضاً
although, she told me recently, I can't say she has big hair,
رغم انها اخبرتني انه لا يجب ان اقول انها تملك شعرٌ كثيف
because if I say she has big hair,
لان الناس سوف يظنون ان قلت ذلك
people will think she's from Texas.
انها من ولاية تكساس
And it's apparently okay to marry a boy from Georgia,
ويبدو انه من الملائم لها الزواج من شاب من جورجيا
but not to have hair from Texas.
ولكن ليس من الملائم ان يكون الشعر من تكساس
And actually, in her defense, if she were here right now,
في الحقيقة .. في دفاعها عن الامر ..ان كانت هنا كانت سوف تقول
she would point out that, when we got married in Georgia,
اننا تزوجنا في جورجيا
there were three questions
وكان هناك على استمارة الزواج 3 اسئلة
on the marriage certificate license,
واحدة منها
the third of which was, "Are you related?"
هل انت مرتبط ؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I said, "Look, in Georgia at least we want to know.
قلت .. حسناً على الاقل في جورجيا يريدون معرفة ذلك ..
In Arkansas they don't even ask."
في اركانساس .. لا يسئلون على الاطلاق
What I didn't tell her is, if she said, "Yes," you could jump.
ما لم اقله لها حينها .. انه لو كتبت " نعم " في ذلك السؤال
You don't need the 30-day waiting period.
يمكننا ان نوثق العقد مباشرة دون الانتظار 30 يوما
Because you don't need the get-to-know-you session at that point.
لانه لا يحتم بعد ذلك فترة اختبار تجريبية
So I wasn't going to tell her about this idea,
حسناً .. لنعد الى قصتنا .. كنت لا اريد ان اخبرها عن مشروعي
but the next day I couldn't control myself, I told her.
ولكن في اليوم التالي لم اتمالك نفسي .. واخبرتها
And she loved the idea,
وقد احبت الفكرة
but she quickly started rejecting my nominees.
وبدأت على الفور برفض اقتراحاتي
She was like, "Well, I love him, but I would never ask him for advice."
وكانت تقول " انا احبه نعم .. ولكن لا يمكن ان اطلب مشورته "
So it turned out that starting a council of dads
لقد تحول مجلس الآباء
was a very efficient way to find out
الى طريقة فعالة
what my wife really thought of my friends.
لكي اعي نظرة زوجتي الى اصدقائي
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So we decided that we needed a set of rules,
لذا قررنا .. ان نصيغ عدة قواعد في هذا الخصوص
and we came up with a number.
وكانت القاعدة الاولى
And the first one was no family, only friends.
التي اصدرتها .. انه لا يجب ان نختار شخصاً من العائلة .. بل حتماً من الاصدقاء
We thought our family would already be there.
لاننا افترضنا ان العائلة سوف تكون قريبة لا محالة
Second, men only.
والشرط الثاني كان يجب ان يكون من في المجلس من الذكور
We were trying to fill the dad-space in the girls' lives.
لاننا كنا نحاول ان نملىء الفراغ الذكوري في حياة البنات
And then third, sort of a dad for every side.
والثالث .. كان يجب ان نختار اصدقاء .. هم آباء
We kind of went through my personality
ومشابهين لشخصيتي
and tried to get a dad who represented each different thing.
وكنا نحاول ان نختار عدة اشخاص لكي يغطوا شخصيتي
So what happened was I wrote a letter to each of these men.
وما حدث هو انني كتبت رسالة لكل واحد من هؤلاء الرجال
And rather than send it,
وبدلا من ان ارسلها
I decided to read it to them in person.
قررت ان ااخذها واقرأها لهم مباشرة
Linda, my wife, joked that it was like having six different marriage proposals.
ليندا .. زوجتي قالت.. ان هذا يبدو وكأنك تتقدم للزواج من 6 رجال
I sort of friend-married each of these guys.
في الحقيقة كان الامر كذلك .. فالامر هنا يشابه الزواج
And the first of these guys was Jeff Schumlin.
وكان اول شخص منهم .. هو جيف سشوملين
Now Jeff led this trip I took to Europe
ان جيف هو من قاد رحلتنا الى اوروبا
when I graduated from high school in the early 1980s.
عندما تخرجنا من المدرسة الثانوية في بداية الثمانينات
And on that first day we were in this youth hostel in a castle.
وفي اليوم الاول كنا بالقرب من قلعة .. وكنا شبابٌ طائش
And I snuck out behind,
وكنت انا اسير خلفه ..
and there was a moat, a fence and a field of cows.
وكان هناك مثل سهل .. محاط به سور .. وفي داخله جمع من الابقار
And Jeff came up beside me and said,
فقال جيف لي حينها
"So, have you ever been cow tipping?"
هل قمت من قبل ببقششة البقر ؟
I was like, "Cow tipping?
تفاجئت " بقششة البقر "!
He was like, "Yeah. Cows sleep standing up.
قال نعم .. الا تعلم . ان الابقار تنام وهي واقفة على ارجلها
So if you approach them from behind, down wind,
وان قدمت اليها من الخلف . .بهدوء
you can push them over and they go thud in the mud."
ودفعتها فجأة .. سوف تقع على الارض وتتلوث بالطين
So before I had a chance to determine whether this was right or not,
وقبل ان اقرر ان كان هذا التصرف صحيح او لا
we had jumped the moat, we had climbed the fence,
كنا قد قفزنا الى الداخل .. وتسلقنا السياج
we were tiptoeing through the dung
وكنا نسير ببطىء عبر الوحل
and approaching some poor, dozing cow.
وكنا نقترب بهدوء من بقرة سائحة
So a few weeks after my diagnosis,
حسناً .. بعد عدة اسابيع من تشخيص مرضي
we went up to Vermont,
ذهبنا الى فرمونت
and I decided to put Jeff as the first person in the Council of Dads.
وقررت ان اضع جيف كاول شخص في مجلس الآباء
And we went to this apple orchard, and I read him this letter.
فذهبت الى موقع عمله .. وقرأت له هذه الرسالة
"Will you help be their dad?"
وقالت له " هل تساعدني بأن تكون والداً لهم ؟ "
And I got to the end -- he was crying and I was crying --
عندما وصلت لنهاية الرسالة .. كانت الدموع تهطل منه .. وكذلك انا
and then he looked at me, and he said, "Yes."
ومن ثم نظر الي وقال .. نعم
I was like, "Yes?"
وانا سعدت بهذا
I kind of had forgotten there was a question at the heart of my letter.
وكنت سأنسى ان هنالك سؤالاً هو لب هذه الرسالة ..
And frankly, although I keep getting asked this,
وفي الحقيقة بت اسئل هذا السؤال على الدوام
it never occurred to me that anybody would turn me down
ولم اكن اتخيل ان احداً ما من اصدقائي سوف يرفض طلبي
under the circumstances.
تبعاً للظروف
And then I asked him a question, which I ended up asking to all the dads
ومن ثم سئلت السؤال الذي كنت انهي به طلبي دوما
and ended up really encouraging me to write this story down in a book.
والذي شجعني لكي اكتب هذه القصة في كتاب
And that was, "What's the one piece of advice
وكان السؤال " ما هي النصيحة
you would give to my girls?"
التي تريد ان تعطيها لبناتي ؟ "
And Jeff's advice was,
وكانت نصيحة جيف حينها
"Be a traveller, not a tourist.
" كونوا مسافرات .. لا سائحات "
Get off the bus. Seek out what's different.
انزلن من الباصات .. اكتشفن ما هو المختلف
Approach the cow."
اقتربن من الابقار ..
"So it's 10 years from now," I said,
لنفترض انه بعد 10 اعوام من الان ..
"and my daughters are about to take their first trip abroad, and I'm not here.
بناتي في صدد القيام برحلتهم الاولى خارج القطر ..وانا لست موجوداً
What would you tell them?"
مالذي سوف تقوله لهم ؟
He said, "I would approach this journey
قال " سوف انصحهم بان يقوموا بالرحلة
as a young child might approach a mud puddle.
كما يقوم الطفل باكتشاف منبسط الطين
You can bend over and look at your reflection in the mirror
يمكنه ان ينحني وينظر اليه .. يمكنه ان يبحث عن صورته في انعكاسه
and maybe run your finger and make a small ripple,
يمكن ان يحرك يديه وان يصنع تموجاً فيه
or you can jump in and thrash around
ويمكن ان يقفز في داخله ويلطخ نفسه به
and see what it feels like, what it smells like."
لكي يشعر به .. ويلمسه .. ويستنشق رائحته
And as he talked he had that glint in his eye
وكان يتحدث وفي عينه الوميض
that I first saw back in Holland --
ذاته الذي رايته في هولندا
the glint that says, "Let's go cow tipping,"
الذي كان يحمسني حينها لكي نقوم ب بقششة الابقار
even though we never did tip the cow,
رغم اننا لم نبقشش اي بقرة
even though no one tips the cow,
ورغم ان احداً لم يقم بذلك
even though cows don't sleep standing up.
ورغم ان الابقار لا تنام واقفة من الاساس !
He said, "I want to see you back here girls, at the end of this experience,
قال سأقول لهن " اريد ان اراكن عندما تعدن من هذه التجربة
covered in mud."
والوحل يغطي اجسادكن "
Two weeks after my diagnosis, a biopsy confirmed
بعد اسبوعين تأكدت نتيجة التشخيص
I had a seven-inch osteosarcoma
كنت املك عظمية طولها 7 بوصات
in my left femur.
في عظمة فخذي اليسرى
Six hundred Americans a year get an osteosarcoma.
فقط 600 امريكي يصابون بالعظمية في الولايات المتحدة الامريكية
Eighty-five percent are under 21.
85 منهم اعمارهم اقل من 21 عام
Only a hundred adults a year
وفقط 100 بالغ في العام
get one of these diseases.
يصاب بواحد من هذه الامراض
Twenty years ago, doctors would have cut off my leg and hoped,
منذ 20 عام كان الاطباء سيقطعون رجلي كحل لهذه المشكلة
and there was a 15 percent survival rate.
ومع توقع بالاستمرار على قيد الحياة بنسبة 15%
And then in the 1980's, they determined
وفي 1980 تم اعتماد
that one particular cocktail of chemo could be effective,
ما يمكن وصفه بانه خليط من المواد الكيميائية والذي وجد انه فعال في معظم الحالات
and within weeks I had started that regimen.
وخلال اسبوع بدأت بالنظام الكيميائي
And since we are in a medical room,
ومنذ ذلك الوقت استقريت في الغرف الطبية
I went through four and a half months of chemo.
وخضت 4 اشهر ونصف من العلاج الكيميائي
Actually I had Cisplatin, Doxorubicin
واستعملت " سييبلاتين , دوكسوروبيسين ..
and very high-dose Methotrexate.
وجرعات كبيرة من ميتوتريكسات "
And then I had a 15-hour surgery
وخضت جراحة استمرت 15 ساعة
in which my surgeon, Dr. John Healey
تحت مبضع الجراح جون هيلي
at Memorial Sloan-Kettering Hospital in New York,
في مستشفى سلوان-كيتيرنيج في نيويورك
took out my left femur
حيث قام بازالة عظمة فخذي اليسرى
and replaced it with titanium.
وابدلها بواحدة من التيتانيوم
And if you did see the Sanjay special,
وان شاهدتم فلم سانجاي
you saw these enormous screws
سوف ترون البراغي
that they screwed into my pelvis.
كيف تم حفرها داخل عظم الحوض
Then he took my fibula from my calf,
ومن ثم اخذ انسجة من القدم
cut it out and then relocated it to my thigh,
وقطعها .. واعاد وضعها في فخذي الجديد
where it now lives.
حيث تنمو الان
And what he actually did was he de-vascularized it from my calf
ان ما قام به بالتحديد هو فك رباطها
and re-vascularized it in my thigh
ومن ثم اعادة ربطها في فخذي
and then connected it
ومن ثم وصلها
to the good parts of my knee and my hip.
الى الاجزاء المتينة في ركبتي ووركي
And then he took out a third of my quadriceps muscle.
ومن ثم قام بازلة ثلث العضلة التي كانت موجودة
This is a surgery so rare
وهذه جراحة نادرة جدا
only two human beings have survived it before me.
لقد عاش اثنين فحسب ممن خاضوها
And my reward for surviving it
ولانني عشت بعد هذه الجراحة ومكافئة على ذلك
was to go back for four more months of chemo.
خضت علاجاً كيميائياً لاربعة اشهر لاحقة
It was, as we said in my house,
لقد كان الامر .. كما كان يصفونه في منزلي
a lost year.
بالسنة الضائعة
Because in those opening weeks, we all had nightmares.
لان الجميع في ليالي الجراحات كان يصاب بالكوابيس
And one night I had a nightmare that I was walking through my house,
وفي ليلة من الليالي كان احد الكوابيس التي عانيت منها
sat at my desk and saw photographs of someone else's children
هو انني دخلت الى منزلي .. ورايت صور اشخاص اخرين .. واولاد اخرين على مكتبي
sitting on my desk.
نعم على مكتبي
And I remember a particular one night that, when you told that story of --
واتذكر ليلة من الليالي .. عندما تخبر هذه القصة
I don't know where you are Dr. Nuland --
انا لا اعلم اين هو الان الدكتور نولاند
of William Sloane Coffin --
من ويليم سلولان كوفين
it made me think of it.
لقد جعلني افكر حقاً في نفسي ..
Because I was in the hospital after, I think it was my fourth round of chemo
في يوم ما وبعد دورتي الرابعة من العلاج الكيميائي
when my numbers went to zero, and I had basically no immune system.
وعندما هبطت خلايا الدم البيضاء لدي للصفر .. ولم اعد املك اي نظام مناعة
And they put me in an infectious disease ward at the hospital.
تم وضعي في غرف عزل الامراض
And anybody who came to see me had to cover themselves in a mask
ولم يكن يستطيع احد الدخول الى تلك الغرفة بدون قناع
and cover all of the extraneous parts of their body.
وجسده بالكامل مُغطى وتم تطهيره
And one night I got a call from my mother-in-law
وذات ليلة تلقيت اتصالا هاتفياً من حماتي
that my daughters, at that time three and a half,
تقولي لي .. ان بناتي .. كان الاتصال في الساعة 3 والنصف
were missing me and feeling my absence.
تقول ان بناتي يشعرن بغيابي
And I hung up the phone,
اغلقت الهاتف ..
and I put my face in my hands,
وضعت وجهي بين كفي
and I screamed this silent scream.
واخذت اصرخ صرخاً صامتاً
And what you said, Dr. Nuland -- I don't know where you are --
كما تسميه يا دكتور نولاند - لا اعلم اين انت الان -
made me think of this today.
لقد تذكرتك اليوم
Because the thought that came to my mind
لان اول فكرة جاءت لعقلي
was that the feeling that I had
هي استذكار ذلك الشعور
was like a primal scream.
الذي يسبق الصراخ
And what was so striking --
انه امرٌ مؤلم
and one of the messages I want to leave you here with today --
ان الرسالة التي اريد ان اترككم معها اليوم
is the experience.
هي التجربة التي خضتها ..
As I became less and less human --
لقد بت اشعر اني اقل بشرية ..
and at this moment in my life, I was probably 30 pounds less than I am right now.
في تلك اللحظة من الحياة .. كنت ازن 30 رطلاً .. اقل مما انا عليه الان
Of course, I had no hair and no immune system.
طبعا بدون اي شعر .. بدو نظام مناعي
They were actually putting blood inside my body.
وكان الدم يضخ الى داخل جسدي
At that moment I was less and less human,
في تلك اللحظة لم اعد اشعر اني بشري
I was also, at the same time,
وكنت ايضاً
maybe the most human I've ever been.
إنسانياً اكثر من اي شخص آخر
And what was so striking about that time
وهذا ما كان محور تلك الاوقات
was, instead of repulsing people,
لانني بدلاً من ان اكون انفر الناس من حولي
I was actually proving to be a magnet for people.
كنت اجذبهم نحوي
People were incredibly drawn.
كان الناس بصورة عجيبة ينجذبون نحوي
When my wife and I had kids, we thought it would be all-hands-on-deck.
عندما انجبنا اطفالنا .. كنا نظن ان الجميع سوف يقف بجانبنا ..
Instead, it was everybody running the other way.
ولكن الامر حدث على العكس تماما
And when I had cancer, we thought it'd be everybody running the other way.
وعندما اصبت بالسرطان كنا نعتقد ان الجميع سوف يدير ظهره ويبتعد
Instead, it was all-hands-on-deck.
ولكن حدث العكس .. كان الجميع منخرطاً معنا
And when people came to me,
وعندما كان الناس يزوروني
rather than being incredibly turned off by what they saw --
بدلاً من ان يبتعدوا من المشهد
I was like a living ghost --
لانني كنت كالشبح
they were incredibly moved
كانوا يتأثرون ..
to talk about what was going on in their own lives.
وكانوا يتحدثون معي عما يجري في حياتهم
Cancer, I found, is a passport to intimacy.
السرطان .. هو جواز سفر للحميمية
It is an invitation, maybe even a mandate,
انه اكتشاف .. انه ربما وسيلة
to enter the most vital arenas of human life,
لدخول حلبات الحيوية الاكثر في حياة الانسان
the most sensitive and the most frightening,
انه المكان المخيف .. والمليء بالمشاعر في ذات الوقت
the ones that we never want to go to,
انه المكان الذي لا يريد احد الذهاب اليه
but when we do go there,
ولكن عندما تصل اليه
we feel incredibly transformed when we do.
انت تتغير تماما
And this also happened to my girls as they began to see,
وهذا يحدث ايضاً لمحيطك .. فبناتي تغيرن
and, we thought, maybe became an ounce more compassionate.
وكنا نعتقد انهن سيغدون شاعريات اكثر ..
One day, my daughter Tybee,
في ذات يوم .. جاءت ابنتي تابي الي
Tybee came to me, and she said, "I have so much love for you in my body, daddy,
وقالت لي .. "والدي انا احبك كثير ..
I can't stop giving you hugs and kisses.
وانا لا استطيع التوقف عن تقبيلك و ضمك الى صدري
And when I have no more love left, I just drink milk,
وعندما اشعر ان الحب نفذ من عندي .. اشرب الحليب
because that's where love comes from."
لأنه المصدر الاول للحب "
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And one night my daughter Eden came to me.
وفي احدى الليالي جاءت الي ابنتي ايدن
And as I lifted my leg out of bed,
وكانت رجلي خارج السرير
she reached for my crutches and handed them to me.
فطالت عكازتي . واعطتني اياهم
In fact, if I cling to one memory of this year,
في الحقيقة ان اردت ان اتشبث بذكرى واحدة في تلك السنة
it would be walking down a darkened hallway
كانت تلك التي كانت عندما كنت اسير في ردهة مظلمة
with five spongy fingers
باصابع قدمي المنتفخة
grasping the handle underneath my hand.
ومحاولا ان اتمسك بحواف الردهة
I didn't need the crutch anymore,
وانا اسير بدون عكازتي
I was walking on air.
كان الامر كما المشي على الهواء
And one of the profound things that happened
وكان احد الاشياء المحورية التي حدثت
was this act of actually connecting to all these people.
هي التواصل مع كل هؤلاء الاشخاص
And it made me think -- and I'll just note for the record --
وهذا جعلني افكر - ويجب ان اقول -
one word that I've only heard once actually
ان الكلمة الوحيدة التي سمعتها في الحقيقة
was when we were all doing Tony Robbins yoga yesterday --
في تمارين توني روبينز البارحة لليوغا
the one word that has not been mentioned in this seminar actually
هي الكلمة التي لم تذكر اليوم على الاطلاق
is the word "friend."
هي كلمة الصديق
And yet from everything we've been talking about --
رغم ان لك شيء كنا نتحدث عنه
compliance, or addiction, or weight loss --
من الادمان .. الى فقدان الوزن .. الى المشاكل
we now know that community is important,
كلها تحتاج المجتمع .. المجتمع محوري بالنسبة لها
and yet it's one thing we don't actually bring in.
وهو الشيء الوحيد الذي لا نتحدث عنه
And there was something incredibly profound
وقد كان هناك شيءٌ اساسي آخر
about sitting down with my closest friends
وهو الجلوس الى اصدقائي المقربين
and telling them what they meant to me.
واخبارهم كم هم مهمون بالنسبة لي
And one of the things that I learned is that over time,
والشيء الذي تعلمته عبر تلك الفترة
particularly men, who used to be non-communicative,
هو ان الرجال الذين هم بالعادة لا يتواصلون بتعابير مباشرة
are becoming more and more communicative.
قد اصبحوا اليوم يتواصلون اكثر بتلك التعابير
And that particularly happened -- there was one in my life --
وهذا حدث في حياتي ..
is this Council of Dads
في مجلس الآباء
that Linda said, what we were talking about,
وقالت ليندا .. ان ما كنا نتحدث عنه
it's like what the moms talk about at school drop-off.
هو نفس ما تتحدث عنه الامهات .. اثناء انتظار اطفالهن
And no one captures this modern manhood to me
ولا احد يعبر لي عن تلك المرحلة
more than David Black.
مثل ديفيد بلاك
Now David is my literary agent.
ان ديفيد هو مندوبي الادبي
He's about five-foot three and a half on a good day,
وهو بطول 5 اقدام .. او 3 ونصف في اليوم الاعتيادي
standing fully upright in cowboy boots.
وهو يرتدي حلة رعاة البقر
And on kind of the manly-male front, he answers the phone --
وهو الرجل الذي طابعه
I can say this I guess because you've done it here --
لا ادري ان كان يمكنني ان اقول هذا هنا ..
he answers the phone, "Yo, motherfucker."
ولكنه عندما يرد على الهاتف يقول " ها . .يا ابن العاهرة "
He gives boring speeches about obscure bottles of wine,
وهو يتحدث دوما احاديث مملة عن قارورات الخمر
and on his 50th birthday he bought a convertible sports car --
وفي عيد ميلاده ال50 اشترى سيارة رياضية مكشوفة السقف
although, like a lot of men, he's impatient; he bought it on his 49th.
في الحقيقة هو مثل العديد من الرجال .. غير صبور .. لقد اشترى تلك السيارة في الواقع في سن 49
But like a lot of modern men, he hugs, he bakes,
ولكنه هو مثل الرجال الجدد .. يطبخ ! يحضن
he leaves work early to coach Little League.
وهو يعود من العمل الى اريكته .. لكي يشاهد الرياضية
Someone asked me if he cried when I asked him to be in the council of dads.
سئلني احدهم .. هل بكى عندما اخبرته عن مجلس الآباء
I was like, "David cries when you invite him to take a walk."
قلت .. ان ديفيد يبكي عندما ادعوه للمشي !
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But he's a literary agent,
ولكنه مندوبي الادبي
which means he's a broker of dreams in a world where most dreams don't come true.
اي انه مضارب"يعمل في البورصة " احلام في عالم الاحلام فيه ضحلة
And this is what we wanted him to capture --
وهذا ما نريده حقا منه
what it means to have setbacks and then aspirations.
ان تجلس بهدوء .. وان تحصل على الالهام
And I said, "What's the most valuable thing you can give to a dreamer?"
قلت له .. ما افضل شيء مهم يمكنك ان تقدمه لشخص حالم ..
And he said, "A belief in themselves."
قال لي حينها .. ان اجعله يثق بنفسه
"But when I came to see you," I said, "I didn't believe in myself.
وعندما قدمت لاتحدث اليه .. كنت لا اثق بنفسي
I was at a wall."
كان مرتطما بجدار
He said, "I don't see the wall," and I'm telling you the same,
قال لي حينها . انا لا ارى الجدار .. عليك بالمثل
Don't see the wall.
لاتنظر الى الجدار
You may encounter one from time to time,
ربما سيواجهك جدار من حين الى اخر
but you've got to find a way to get over it, around it, or through it.
ولكن عليك ان تجد طريقة لتجاوزه .. الالتفاف حوله .. اختراقه
But whatever you do, don't succumb to it.
ولكن مهما حدث .. لا تتوقف امامه
Don't give in to the wall.
لا تستسلم للجدار
My home is not far from the Brooklyn Bridge,
ان منزلي ليس بعيدا من جسر بروكلين
and during the year and a half I was on crutches,
واثناء تلك السنة والنصف التي قضيتها على العكازتين
it became a sort of symbol to me.
بدا لي هذا الجسر كرمز
So one day near the end of my journey,
في احد الايام بعد انتهاء جولتي
I said, "Come on girls, let's take a walk across the Brooklyn Bridge."
قلت " يا بنات هيا لكي نسير عبر جسر برولكين "
We set out on crutches.
لقد ذهبت بالعكازات
I was on crutches, my wife was next to me,
كانت زوجتي بقربي ..
my girls were doing these rockstar poses up ahead.
كانت بناتي يقفن مثل ابطال السينما على طول الجسر
And because walking was one of the first things I lost,
ولان السير هو اول ما افتقدته
I spent most of that year
قضيت معظم تلك السنة
thinking about this most elemental of human acts.
افكر بهذه الميزة الانسانية الكبيرة
Walking upright, we are told,
المشي مستقيم الظهر ..
is the threshold of what made us human.
انه الذي جعل الانسان يصل الى ما هو عليه الان
And yet, for the four million years humans have been walking upright,
وعلى مدى 4 ملاين عام نحن نسير منتصبي القامة
the act is essentially unchanged.
ان هذا الفعل المحوري لم يتغير
As my physical therapist likes to say,
كما يقول معالجي الفيزيائي
"Every step is a tragedy waiting to happen."
ان كل خطوة هي عبارة عن مآساة يمكن ان تحصل
You nearly fall with one leg,
فانت عندما ترفع احدى اقدامك .. تكون على وشك ان تسقط
then you catch yourself with the other.
فتتلقفك قدمك الاخرى
And the biggest consequence of walking on crutches --
واكبر مشكلة في السير على العكازات
as I did for a year and a half --
التي كنت استخدمها لطيلة عام ونصف
is that you walk slower.
هو انك تسير ببطء
You hurry,
عليك ان تسرع دوما
you get where you're going, but you get there alone.
وعليك ان تصل الى المكان المطلوب .. ولكن دوما تصل متاخرا .. ودوما تصل وحيدا
You go slow, you get where you're going,
انت تسير ببطىء اينما اردت السير
but you get there with this community
وانت تصل هناك مع المجتمع
you built along the way.
الذي احاط بك طيلة الطريق
At the risk of admission, I was never nicer
ولكي اكون صادقاً .. لم اكن حسن الخلق
than the year I was on crutches.
في السنة التي كنت فيها على العكازين
200 years ago,
منذ 200 عام
a new type of pedestrian appeared in Paris.
ظهر نظام مشي جديد في باريس
He was called a "flaneur," one who wanders the arcades.
كان يدعى فلانور .. وهو يعني من يتامل بالاروقة
And it was the custom of those flaneurs
وهذا النظام فلانور
to show they were men of leisure
كان قد ظهر من اجل رفاهية خاصة
by taking turtles for walks
انه يقوم على اخذ سلحفاة للمشي
and letting the reptile set the pace.
اي وضع سلحفاة في طريق
And I just love this ode to slow moving.
والاستمتاع بالسير معها .. ببطء
And it's become my own motto for my girls.
وهذا ما بدأ يصبح شعاري مع الفتيات
Take a walk with a turtle.
خذوا سلحفاة للسير
Behold the world in pause.
استمتعوا بالعالم .. توقفوا قليلا
And this idea of pausing
استمتعوا بالهدوء بالتوقف
may be the single biggest lesson I took from my journey.
انه الدرس الاكبر الذي تعلمته من رحلتي هذه مع المرض
There's a quote from Moses
هناك اقتباس من النبي موسى
on the side of the Liberty Bell,
على جانب جرس الحرية
and it comes from a passage in the book of Leviticus,
وجاء من كتاب سفر اللاويين
that every seven years you should let the land lay fallow.
وهو يعني ان كل سبع سنوات يجب ان تترك الارض بعلاً
And every seven sets of seven years,
وكل سبع سبع مرات
the land gets an extra year of rest
يجب ان تترك الارض سنة اضافية بعلاً
during which time all families are reunited
واثناءها .. تتوحد العائلات
and people surrounded with the ones they love.
وتحيط بعضها ببعض
That 50th year is called the jubilee year,
ان السنة ال50 تلك تدعى سنة جوبيلي
and it's the origin of that term.
وهي محور كل الانظمة
And though I'm shy of 50,
وانا كنت خجولاً من العام 50
it captures my own experience.
انه يعني انني كبرت .. ان تجربتي نضجت
My lost year was my jubilee year.
ان سنة جوبيلي .. كانت سنتي الضائعة
By laying fallow,
وبالمضي قدماً
I planted the seeds for a healthier future
زرعت بذوراً لمستقبل اكثر صحة واشراقاً
and was reunited with the ones I love.
وكنت قد توحدت مع من احب
Come the one year anniversary of my journey,
وبعد مرور عام على رحتلي تلك
I went to see my surgeon, Dr. John Healey --
ذهبت لرؤية الطبيب جون هيلي
and by the way, Healey, great name for a doctor.
وبالمناسبة اسم هيلي ملائم جداً لطبيبي ( هيلي = الشافي )
He's the president of the International Society of Limb Salvage,
انه رئيس الجمعية الدولية لانقاذ الاطراف
which is the least euphemistic term I've ever heard.
وهو تعبير وصف لتلك الجمعية مجحف كثيرا
And I said, "Dr. Healey, if my daughters come to you one day
فقلت له " دكتور هيلي .. ان قدمت اليك بناتي ذات يوم "
and say, 'What should I learn from my daddy's story?'
وقلن لك " مالذي يجب ان نتعلمه من قصة والدنا ؟ "
what would you tell them?"
مالذي سوف تقوله لهن
He said, "I would tell them what I know,
قال " ساخبرهم ما اعرفه
and that is everybody dies,
كل الناس تموت
but not everybody lives.
ولكن ليس كل لناس تبقى على قيد الحياة " تعيش حياة حقيقية "
I want you to live."
اريدكم ان تبقوا على قيد الحياة "
I wrote a letter to my girls
لقد كتبت رسالة الى بناتي
that appears at the end of my book, "The Council of Dads,"
موجودة في كتاب " مجلس الآباء "
and I listed these lessons,
وكتبت فيها كل هذه الدروس
a few of which you've heard here today:
بعض منها سمعتموه اليوم
Approach the cow, pack your flipflops,
اقترب من البقرة .. اشتري زحافات
don't see the wall,
لا تنظر الى الجدار
live the questions,
عش بالفضول
harvest miracles.
احصد المعجزات
As I looked at this list -- to me it was sort of like a psalm book of living --
وكما انظر اليه اليوم .. انه يبدو كما لو انه ترنيمة عيش
I realized, we may have done it for our girls,
لقد ادركت .. ان ما كنت اقوم به لبناتي
but it really changed us.
قد غيرني انا ايضاً
And that is, the secret of the Council of Dads,
وهذا هو سر مجلس الآباء
is that my wife and I did this
انا وزوجتي عندما قمنا بذلك
in an attempt to help our daughters,
لكي نساعد بناتنا
but it really changed us.
ساعدنا انفسنا وتغيرنا
So I stand here today
وانا اقف اليوم
as you see now, walking without crutches or a cane.
اسير اليوم بدون عكازات .. ولا عصي
And last week I had my 18-month scans.
وفي الشهر الماضي كنت قد اجريت فحصي في الشهر ال18
And as you all know,
وكما تعلمون جميعاً
anybody with cancer has to get follow-up scans.
او اي شخص اصيب بالسرطان .. انه يتوجب عليه القيام دوماً بفحوصات دورية
In my case it's quarterly.
وفي حالتي ربع سنوية
And all the collective minds in this room, I dare say,
ولا اعتقد ان احداً في هذه الغرفة
can never find a solution for scan-xiety.
على الاطلاق يمكنه ان يجد حلاً للقلق قبل الفحوصات الدورية
As I was going there, I was wondering, what would I say
كنت حينها ذاهب الى هناك وانا اتسائل
depending on what happened here.
عن ما سوف اتحدث به هنا .. لان ذلك كان محوري لهذا الحديث
I got good news that day,
لقد تلقيت اخبارا جيدة ذلك اليوم
and I stand here today cancer-free,
انا اليوم قد شفيت تماما من السرطان
walking without aid
وانا اسير بدون اي مساعدة
and hobbling forward.
واتامل بمستقبل مشرق
And I just want to mention briefly in passing -- I'm past my time limit --
واريد ان اذكر - لقد تجاوزت الوقت المخصص لي -
but I just want to briefly mention in passing
ولكن يجب ان اذكر
that one of the nice things that can come out of a conference like this
ان في مؤتمر كهذا
is, at a similar meeting,
وفي اجتماع كهذا
back in the spring,
في الربيع الماضي
Anne Wojcicki heard about our story
آن وجيكي سمعت قصتنا
and very quickly -- in a span of three weeks --
وبسرعة كبيرة - خلال 3 اسابيع -
put the full resources of 23andMe,
جمعت كل المعلومات من 23 شخص وانا
and we announced an initiative in July
واعلنت عن مبادرة في شهر يوليو\تموز
to get to decode the genome
لنفك الشفرة الجينية (الجينيوم البشري)
of anybody, a living person
لاي شخص .. لاي انسان
with a heart tissue, bone sarcoma.
من خلال نسيج من القلب .. او عينة من العظام
And she told me last night, in the three months since we've done it,
واخبرتني الليلة الماضية .. انه منذ 3 اشهر على الانطلاق
we've gotten 300 people who've contributed to this program.
ساهم معنا 300 شخص في هذا البرنامج
And the epidemiologists here will tell you,
وخبراء الاوبئة سوف يقولون لك
that's half the number of people who get the disease
ان هؤلاء ال300 شخص هم نصف من يصابون بنفس مرضي
in one year in the United States.
كل عام في الولايات المتحدة الامريكية
So if you go to 23andMe,
اذا ان ذهبتم الى موقع 23andMe
or if you go to councilofdads.com, you can click on a link.
او الى موقع councilofdads.com يمكنكم المساهمة
And we encourage anybody to join this effort.
وفي دفع الجهود الرامية الى هذا الامر
But I'll just close what I've been talking about
وسوف انهي هذه المحادثة
by leaving you with this message:
بهذه الرسالة :
May you find an excuse to reach out to some long-lost pal,
ربما ستجد سبباً لكي تتواصل مع صديق قديم
or to that college roommate,
او زميل دراسي
or to some person you may have turned away from.
او شخص تخليت عنه منذ زمن طويل
May you find a mud puddle to jump in someplace,
وربما ستجد حقل وحل ستُسعد بالقفز فيه
or find a way to get over, around, or through any wall
وربما سوف تجدر طريقة لكي تخترق\تتجاوز\تلتف على الجدار الذي
that stands between you and one of your dreams.
يقف عائقاً بينك وبين احلامك
And every now and then,
وبين كل هذا
find a friend, find a turtle,
جد صديقاً .. جد سلحفاة
and take a long, slow walk.
واستمتع بمشي هادىء .. بمشي بطيء
Thank you very much.
شكراً جزيلا
(Applause)
(تصفيق)